Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union PE.006
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union
1920-1991
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.006
3 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
The Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. It consists largely of contracts and agreements between the Union and various companies, both from the United States and Canada, and ranging in date from the 1940s to the 1980s. The collection also contains constitutions, circular letters, reports, fliers, and pamphlets and publications, as well as articles and clippings about the Union. In the collection are materials from locals of the United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union as well as materials from its predecessors, including the Cloth Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union and the United Hatters of North America.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: Series I: Agreements and Contracts, 1940-1991; Series II: General Files, 1920-1978. Folders are arranged alphabetically within series.
Historical/Biographical Note
The United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union (UHCMW) was formed in 1934 by the amalgamation of United Hatters of North America and the Cloth Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union. The United Hatters of North America was established in New York in 1896 as the result of the merger of two Knights of Labor-affiliated unions in the men's hat industry, the Hat Makers and the Hat Finishers. The Cloth Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union was established in New York in 1901, as the United Cloth Hat and Cap Makers of North America (superseding the Cloth Hat and Cap Operators Union), and took its final name (adding Millinery Workers) in 1918. In 1983 the UHCMW joined the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, which in turn merged in 1995 with the International Ladies Garment Workers Union to form UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees).
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union largely consists of agreements and contracts, it also contains constitutions and reports as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, circular letters, newspaper clippings, programs, pamphlets and other publications.
Series I: Agreements and Contracts, 1940-1989, consists of legal size agreements and contracts with companies around the United States and Canada.
Series II: General Files, 1920-1978, contains material from the United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union, however, this series also contains material from the Cloth Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union and the United Hatters of North America, two predecessor unions. The General Files consist of constitutions and financial reports as well as publications put out by the National Recovery Administration on codes of fair conduct for the hat manufacturing industry. There are fliers from the Millinery and Hatters Committee for Wallace, documenting the committee's support of Henry A. Wallace's bids for the US presidency in 1944 and 1948. The collection also contains a small number of fliers and ephemera regarding the Union Label Campaign and various union and national elections. In addition to material from the international and national bodies of the United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union, there are also files from locals, including Locals 3 and 8, both from New York City. The file on Local 8 contains financial reports, local election fliers, rank and file produced circular letters, and a constitution dated 1922, at that time under the auspices of the United Hatters of North America.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers Union Photographs (PHOTOS 175)
United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union Records (TAM 054)
United Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers International Union, Millinery Workers Joint Board Records (WAG 41)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
Constitutions.; Agreements.; Circular letters.; Reports.; Publications (documents); Fliers (printed matter); Contracts; Labor unions; Clippings (information artifacts); Articles.; Labor unions -- Elections -- United States.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Broadsides (notices); Brochures.; United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union. Local 8; United Hatters of North America; Cloth Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers' International Union; United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union
- Series I: Agreements and Contracts, 1940-1991
  - Adjustable Hat Company, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
  - Allied Hat Manufacturers, 1956-1970 (Box 1)
  - American Millinery Manufacturers, 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - AOCO Limited, 1972-1978 (Box 1)
  - Associated Buckram Shape Manufacturers, Inc., 1949-1952 (Box 1)
  - Association of Millinery Manufacturers, 1963-1974 (Box 1)
  - Atlantic Hatblock Corporation, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Atson's Product Corporation, 1961-1974 (Box 1)
  - Bako Uniform Cap Corporation, 1968-1982 (Box 1)
  - Baltimore Hat Sewers, Inc., 1962-1970 (Box 1)
  - Barton Rough Hat Company, Inc., 1963-1968 (Box 1)
  - Benay-Albee Novelty Company, 1961-1989 (Box 1)
  - Bernstein Hat Company, 1966-1981 (Box 1)
  - Bertha Hat Company, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Pete Brooks Hats, Inc., 1966 (Box 1)
  - Biltmore Hats, 1958-1981 (Box 1)
  - Biltmore Hats Western Limited, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Binder Brothers Inc., 1977 (Box 1)
  - Bleber-Godman Associates, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Byer-Rolnick, 1973-1979 (Box 1)
  - Champ Hats, 1959-1970 (Box 1)
  - Charu-Canton Hat Company, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Chaucer Leather Limited, 1973 (Box 1)
  - C.N. Clark Company, Inc., 1962-1975 (Box 1)
  - Classic Cap Company, 1974-1979 (Box 1)
  - Crown Cap Manufacturers, 1966-1986 (Box 1)
  - Danbury Hat Company, 1975-1983 (Box 1)
  - David Hat Company, 1960-1966 (Box 1)
  - Eastern Women's Headwear Association, Inc., 1940-1958 (Box 1)
  - Empire Hat Block Corporation, 1965 (Box 1)
  - FDR Industries, 1972-1980 (Box 1)
  - Feld Man Machine Works, 1965-1975 (Box 1)
  - Franklin and Lasoff, Inc., 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Frielich Leather Corporation, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Gelhaar Uniform Company, 1966-1972 (Box 1)
  - General Cap Corporation, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Hat Corporation of America, 1944-1970 (Box 1)
  - Hat Frame Manufacturers Association of New York, Inc., 1955 (Box 1)
  - Hatters Machinery and Equipment Association, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Henschel Manufacturing Company, 1974-1979 (Box 1)
  - Holly Manufacturing, Inc., 1981 (Box 1)
  - Hubbard Dyers, Limited, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Imperial Caps, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Imperial Optical Company, Limited, 1971-1975 (Box 2)
  - Imperial Optical Company, Limited, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - Imperial Optical Company, Limited: Lens Plant, 1969-1977 (Box 2)
  - Imperial Optical Company, Limited: Prescription Laboratories, 1971-1978 (Box 2)
  - Independent Manufacturers, 1969-1977 (Box 2)
  - Iona Hat Company, 1963-1966 (Box 2)
  - J.A. Miller Company, 1966-1982 (Box 2)
  - Jay Gerish Company and Agrest Dying Company, 1969-1980 (Box 2)
  - Jay Lord Hatters, 1965-1977 (Box 2)
  - Kahn Optical Company, Limited, 1973 (Box 2)
  - James Shaen, Limited, 1973-1977 (Box 2)
  - Jan Leslie Company, 1965-1969 (Box 2)
  - L. Kleinman, 1966-1975 (Box 2)
  - Lowenthal and Hess, Inc., 1957-1969 (Box 2)
  - Lynbrooke Hat Company, Inc., 1972-1980 (Box 2)
  - Malrov United Hat Company, 1966-1981 (Box 2)
  - Manual Hat Company, 1969-1975 (Box 2)
  - Mar Bee Hat Company, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Marty the Hatter (Van Dyke Hatters), 1970-1977 (Box 2)
  - Massachusetts Millinery Manufacturers Association, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Mass Hat and Novelty Corporation, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Midway Industries, Limited, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Midwest-Northeastern Hat Company, 1974-1982 (Box 2)
  - Millinery Manufacturers of New Jersey, Inc., 1943-1957 (Box 2)
  - Monarch Optical Manufacturers, Limited, 1972-1980 (Box 2)
  - Montreal Hat and Cap Manufacturing Company, 1964-1980 (Box 2)
  - Mutual Electric and Machinery Corporation, 1977 (Box 2)
  - National Association of Ladies' Hatters, Inc., 1943-1949 (Box 2)
  - National Headwear Manufacturers Association, 1965-1972 (Box 2)
  - New York Association of Wholesalers of Ladies' and Children's Hats, Inc., 1942 (Box 2)
  - Oakley Optical, Limited, 1973 (Box 2)
  - O'Connor-Goldstein Company, 1961-1982 (Box 2)
  - Ontario Cap Manufacturers Association, 1972-1991 (Box 2)
  - Oxford Hat and Cap Company, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Philadelphia Millinery Association, 1946-1979 (Box 2)
  - Pioneer Block Company, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Pittsburgh Hat Works, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Puma Hat Company, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Resistol Hats, 1971-1985 (Box 2)
  - Rosiclare Manufacturing Company, 1979-1989 (Box 2)
  - S&B Headwear, Inc., 1969 (Box 3)
  - S&M Cap Company, 1960-1969 (Box 3)
  - S&S Hat Company, 1972-1983 (Box 3)
  - St. Louis Cap Front Manufacturing Company, 1966-1979 (Box 3)
  - Salmar Contractors, Inc., undated (Box 3)
  - Sharon Hats, Inc., 1969 (Box 3)
  - Society Brand, Inc., 1969-1975 (Box 3)
  - Sportwear Industries, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Star Headwear, 1977-1987 (Box 3)
  - Sue Ellen Hat Company, 1966-1975 (Box 3)
  - Sue Hatter of Florida, Inc., 1969-1974 (Box 3)
  - Ted Kleinman, Inc., 1975-1981 (Box 3)
  - Toppers, Inc., 1959-1976 (Box 3)
  - Uniform Manufacturers Exchange, Inc., 1964-1967 (Box 3)
  - Uniform Manufacturers Exchange, Inc., 1969-1979 (Box 3)
  - United Manufacturing Company, 1971-1974 (Box 3)
  - Universal Hat and Cap Manufacturing Company, Inc., 1964-1984 (Box 3)
  - Wagner Hat Company, Inc., 1968-1970 (Box 3)
  - Wentworth Uniform Cap Company, 1977-1980 (Box 3)
  - West Penn Hat and Cap Corporation, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
  - Wiedeman Hat Company, 1957-1970 (Box 3)
  - William Scully, Limited, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Wood Hat Block Manufacturers Association, 1967-1975 (Box 3)
- Series II: General Files, 1920-1978
  - Cloth Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers' International Union/Cloth Hat and Cap Makers of North America, 1920-1927 (Box 3)
  - Constitutions, undated (Box 3)
  - Constitutions, 1934-1939 (Box 3)
  - Constitutions, 1944-1946 (Box 3)
  - Constitutions, 1953, 1959, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Conventions: Reports from Officers, 1936-1939, 1948, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Financial Reports, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Headgear Workers American Labor Party Club, undated (Box 3)
  - Headgear Workers' Credit Union, 1924, undated (Box 3)
  - Headgear Workers Lyceum, 1920 (Box 3)
  - Lawlor, Martin, undated (Box 3)
  - Local 3 (Straw and Panama Hatters, New York, NY), undated (Box 3)
  - Local 8 (New York, NY), 1922, 1936-1948, undated (Box 3)
  - Local 20 and 56 (Millinery Workers' Union) (St. Louis), 1936 (Box 3)
  - Local 24, 1945-1952, undated (Box 3)
  - Local 57, 1952 (Box 3)
  - Local 75 (Beacon, NY), undated (Box 3)
  - Local 125 (Corsicana, TX), 1958 (Box 3)
  - Men's Hat Department, 1935, undated (Box 3)
  - Millinery and Hatters Committee for Wallace (New York, NY), circa 1944-1948 (Box 3)
  - Millinery Workers Health and Retirement Funds (New York, NY), 1946-1952 (Box 3)
  - National Recovery Administration: Codes of Fair Conduct for Hat Manufacturing, 1934 (Box 3)
  - New Leader (AFL Publication), Increasing Circulation of, 1938 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles on, 1946-1961 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and Publications, 1941, undated (Box 3)
  - Union Label Campaign, circa 1966 (Box 3)
  - United Hatters of North America, 1920-1927 (Box 3)
  - United Ticket Campaign, undated (Box 3)